All right, everyone, so we were having a look at the first step in a journey that is getting the JDK installed setting up our IDE, which honestly didn't take much time because IntelliJ is so good and we just got a project that we could just run and now in this video, we'll just have a look at what this thing means here, right.
And why is it important for you to understand it early on and we'll just start with the public class app, right. And this one here. So what happens is everything in Java needs to be inside a class and just a note there in the in some of the recent versions of Java.
We don't really need a class to be written for a program to be written and executed and I'll just put a separate video on the updates, right. But for now, because as I said, for the overwhelming majority of developers worldwide were working in Java teams working in Java companies working in Java.
They're still using earlier versions, let's say Java 17 or 15 or 11 for that fact. And in those versions, we still require the class to be written and that's why throughout the scores will stick to the class being there inside every Java program, but otherwise, as I said, I'll just have a separate video for you to know what will those changes and where we could do without the class keyboard.
But for now, this is a class and I'll have a separate video on classes and objects, right, because it's very imperative, it's imperative for you to understand how classes and objects work and how they are at the center of everything that we do in an object oriented programming language like Java.
But for now, everything needs to be in a class and how do we define a class in Java you do that with the keyword class and public let's get rid of that for now we don't need it for now until we come across scoop and there would be a separate video on that.
So for now you can just do without public I've just said class and then this is the identifier right and now identifiers are which identifies something else uniquely and in this case, this identifier is identifying this new class that I'm creating a line number 17 or line number seven sorry.
So now identifiers there are certain rules to be followed in Java that is they should not start with a number they should not have special symbols except underscore and currency characters which are allowed and then there are some recommendations and in Java we follow the cable case and the cable case says that if you are declaring class identifiers, they should start with a capital letter.
That's why you see is in capital here right and if they're made of one of more than one words, then every word should have the first letter in caps like for example if I'd call this as app right.
So this would have been the right way of declaring the class name following cable case right, but because this is just one word so it has to be in capital.
And cable case says how do you define methods and functions, they should be in all smalls if it's just made of one word, but if it's made of more than one words, then every word should have the first letter in caps except the first word.
That is like this main is a method it's an all small but let's say it was called main tree then m small p capital every subsequent word should have the first letter in caps and variables the same right as methods.
And then how do you define constants in Java with cable case, they should be in all caps right so that you would know having a look at them from far away, this is a constant it's not a variable and cable case it's very important you digest this concept early on because it would just help you to know or read someone else code appropriately easily and and quickly because you know what would be a last what would be a method and what would be a variable for that.
So that's why following the rules and recommendations we've called this classes app this would be named app and then the curly braces because everything in Java which is a class or a method for that fact should have a curly brace and then the ending closing curly brace as well.
So that we have defined this main method which is special why the specialty lies in for running your Java applications you at least need the main method again more and updates separately but for now it followed this right.
That is public static void main because for the majority of the programs that you'll come across in your teams on the Internet they would have a class they would have a main method.
It's the entry point of your program is the exit point of your program like C and C++ C style programming languages they always have to have the main method and the main method here is it should be public should be static should be white and it should have a string array arguments.
What is this required for now this is required if you ever wanted to take user input from runtime right so but the signature should match exactly the same otherwise it would not be considered the main method.
And the main has its own body that is a curly braces start the curly braces end and within this at line number 11 we've just printed something on the console.
How do you do that in C with printf in C++ that was see out in a language like PHP it's echo in Java it's system throughout print ln and that is hello world and once we run this we should get hello world on screen that is what we get.
So now what is the importance of this program that is you will see this in every Java program at least one class and the main the mandatory main method needs to be declared somewhere not just.
At a particular place but in one of the classes because that's where the execution starts in a Java program that is from the public static void main string array arguments and the only thing that you can replace on line number 10 or line number nine for that fact is the name of this.
I can call it ABC but arcs is more appropriate let's just stick to that right otherwise it has to be public has to be static wide and main as well right and as you saw we run this and we got hello world on screen so that's the most basic Java program you're ever going to come across but it holds significant importance as I told you why so I'll see you in the next video.